Guide to the William Rufus Shafter Papers
Department of Special Collections
William Rufus Shafter papers
1862-1945
1862-1904
M0072
Shafter, William Rufus, 1835-1906
4 linear feet
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The Shafter Collection represents the papers and other materials assembled by General William R. Shafter during his many years of military service. As might be expected, the Collection includes personal and official correspondence, military papers (orders, reports, rosters, etc.), broadsides, maps, cartoons, photographs, miscellaneous printed material, and newspaper clippings. Correspondence composes approximately eighty percent of the Collection, the majority of which concerns the period from 1862 to 1994. In addition, a small collection of materials assembled by Shafter's son-in-law, William H. McKittrick, has been added to the basic Shafter Collection.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Stewart Edward White, of Burlingame, executor of the William H. McKittrick estate, 1938.
Custodial History
Upon Shafter's death his papers passed into the possession of Mr. and Mrs. William H. McKittrick. Mrs. McKittrick was the former Mary Shafter.
Biography / Administrative History
William Rufus Shafter, born on October 16, 1835, at Galesburg, was said to have been the first white male born in Kalamazoo County, Michigan. His father, Hugh Morris Shafter, came to what was then the frontier from Windsor, Vermont, and built his future home, a log cabin. He returned to Vermont to marry Eliza Sumner of Massachusetts. The newly married couple then proceeded to Michigan and to their small farm.
When he was not helping his father on the farm, Shafter attended common school in Galesburg. Anxious for further education, he began teaching in 1856. Eventually he attended Prairie Seminary in Richland County, where in 1861 he learned of the outbreak of the Civil War. He promptly enlisted in the Union Army for three years.
On August 22, 1861, Shafter was appointed a First Lieutenant of the Seventh Michigan Infantry, a regiment which served a year with the Army of the Potomac and saw action at Yorktown, Fair Oaks, Malvern Hill, West Point, and Savage Station. At the age of twenty-six, he was promoted to a Major in the Nineteenth Michigan Infantry. It was with this regiment that, after a fierce struggle, he was taken prisoner at Thompson's Station on March 5, 1863. Shafter was exchanged that May, and by June of 1863 was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel of the Seventeenth U.S. Colored Infantry. He remained with this unit for the duration of the Civil War, leading them through the battles before Nashville on December 15-16, 1864. After the surrender at Appomattox, Lieutenant Colonel Shafter received the Brevet of Brigadier General, U.S. Volunteers for gallant and meritorious service. Upon the reorganization of the U.S. Army he was mustered out of service on November 2, 1866.
Shafter had impressed his commanding officers throughout the War. They described him as brave, gallant, prompt, intelligent, and a good disciplinarian. Due to his outstanding record, he received many strong recommendations for permanent appointment in the reorganized army. Unlike many officers who passed from the temporary to the permanent establishment of the army at the end of the war, Shafter spent no time in civilian life.
His first appointment in the U.S. Army was that of Lieutenant Colonel of the Forty-first U.S. Infantry on July 28, 1866. Three years later, he was assigned to the Twenty-fourth U.S. Colored Infantry, with which he served ten years. For the most part, those years were spent on the Mexican frontier. There, he was relatively successful in controlling marauding bands of Indians and Mexican bandits. It was during this period that Shafter received the appellation Pecos Bill for leading his hungry and thirsty command to the Pecos River in Texas.
In 1879, Shafter was promoted to Colonel of the First U.S. Infantry, a position he held for nearly eighteen years. From 1879 he commanded his regiment in Dakota, Texas, and Arizona, was Superintendent of the Recruiting Service in New York, and again commanded his unit in Arizona, California, and South Dakota. Shafter was post commandant at Angel Island from 1891 to 1897, except for a period in 1894, when he led a battalion against strikers in Los Angeles and Santa Monica.
For his most distinguished gallantry in action at the battle of Fair Oaks, Virginia, May 31, 1862, Shafter received the Congressional Medal of Honor. This decoration, given in 1895, brought him to the attention of high-ranking officers in Washington.
President McKinley acknowledged his rank and record by commissioning him Brigadier General on May 3, 1897. The Senate promptly confirmed his appointment, and Shafter became commander of the Department of California, assigned to the same station where he had so long been post commander.
Shafter's call to fame came with the outbreak of the Spanish-American War in 1898. He was commissioned Major General of Volunteers and placed in command of an expeditionary force. After a month's delay awaiting final orders, the expedition embarked for Santiago de Cuba on June 12, 1898. The troops landed June 22. By the seventeenth of July, the Spanish forces had capitulated to Shafter's Fifth Army.
During the armistice which preceded the final surrender of the Spaniards, the health of the American troops was severely impaired by malaria, yellow fever, and unsanitary conditions in the field. Though his campaign was successful, Shafter faced sharp criticism from the public and the press for conditions over which he had no control.
Despite the outcry following the return of the troops, Shafter's reputation remained intact. He returned to his regular army rank of Brigadier General and assumed command of the Department of California at San Francisco. He retained this post until October 16, 1899, at which time he was retired from active service. However, as a gesture of respect, the President allowed him to continue in this command under his volunteer rank of Major General until June 30, 1901.
After his final retirement Shafter moved to Bakersfield, California, where he lived with his daughter, Mary, and her husband, W. H. McKitterick, his wife, Harriet, having died in 1898. Throughout his residence in California, Shafter maintained old friendships and remained active in veterans' organizations such as the Grand Army of the Republic, and the Society of the Army of Santiago de Cuba.
On November 12, 1906, William R. Shafter succumbed to pneumonia. He was buried with military honors at the Presidio of San Francisco in the presence of many distinguished individuals. Although after his death, Shafter's memory faded quickly from public consciousness, history has preserved the relative value of his achievements.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Shafter Collection represents the papers and other materials assembled by General William R. Shafter during his many years of military service. As might be expected, the Collection includes personal and official correspondence, military papers (orders, reports, rosters, etc.), broadsides, maps, cartoons, photographs, miscellaneous printed material, and newspaper clippings. Correspondence composes approximately eighty percent of the Collection, the majority of which concerns the period from 1862 to 1994. In addition, a small collection of materials assembled by Shafter's son-in-law, William H. McKittrick, has been added to the basic Shafter Collection.
The Shafter Papers are of value to the student of American history. Two particular groups of papers merit special emphasis: those relating to the expeditions to counter Indian and Mexican bandits in the southwest following the Civil War, and those concerned with the Spanish-American War of 1898. Shafter's participation in the activities in the southwestern United States reflects the difficulties faced by an American border command charged with trying to control elusive marauders, as well as the sensitive political situation in which that command had to discharge its duties. The Spanish War materials include copies of official orders and correspondence prepared by Shafter during the Santiago Campaign as well as papers relating to the peace negotiations. Included are comments concerning not only the actual conduct of military affairs, but also the political and social attitudes toward the Army, the Spanish, and the Cuban allies of the United States.
The Shafter Papers provide a valuable and illuminating insight into the career and character of an historically important individual who is relatively unknown today. Although a biography of William R. Shafter has yet to be written, his papers and personal files provide an intimate review of the man and the times in which he lived.
Shafter Materials in Other Repositories
As located in the National Union Catalogue of Manuscript Collections and the List of Record Groups of the National Archives and Records Service
LIBRARY OF CONGRESS
MS64-769 Henry C. Corbin Papers
UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN
Michigan Historical Collection MS 1363 Military Topics
MS 65-475 John Patton Papers
WILLIAM L. CLEMENTS LIBRARY MS 60-1433 Russell A. Alger Papers
NATIONAL ARCHIVES
94 NNMO Adjutant General's Office, 1780's-1917
108 NNMO Army, Headquarters of the
395 NNMO Army Continental Commands, United States, 1821-1920
192 NNG Commissary General of Subsistance, Office of
140 NNFN Cuba, Military Government of
199 NNFN Cuba, Provisional Government of
77 NNMO Engineers, Office of the Chief of
153 NNMO Judge Advocate General (Army), Office of the
99 NNG Paymaster General, Office of the
92 NNMO Quartermaster General, Office of the
112 NNMO Records of the Office of the Surgeon General (Army)
50 NNFL Records of the Treasurer of the United States
15 NNMO Records of the Veterans Administration
111 NNMO Signal Officer, Office of the Chief
107 NNMO War, Office of the Secretary
Further information on Shafter can be found with the aid of National Archives Microfilm Publications and Preliminary Inventory of the Records of the United States Army Command, 1-4 (Record Group 393). See especially records of the Department of Texas, the East, Pacific, and the Dakotas. There are also a variety of records extant at particular posts where Shafter was stationed. Another extremely helpful research tool is The US Army and the Spanish-American War Era, 1895-1910 (Special Bibliographic Series Number 9 of the U.S. Army Military History Research Collection published at Carlisle Barracks, Pennsylvania). This work by Thomas E. Kelly is a listing of only those materials physically included in the U.S. Army Military History Research Collection at Carlisle Barracks, Pennsylvania.
Publications included in the Shafter Collection
Beyer, W. F., and O. F. Keydel (Eds.), Though Wounded, Remained at His Post. Deeds of Valor No. 2. Detroit: The Perrien-Keydel Publishing Co., 1900. Roll VI, Folder 65.
Hale, Edward E. (Ed.), The Capture of Havana in 1762 by the Forces of George III. Cambridge, Massachusetts: The Cooperative Printing Society, 1898. This is now deposited in the Special Collections Department of Stanford University.
Humphrey, C. F., Colonel, Expedition to Santiago under the Command of William R. Shafter, U.S.V., Report to the Quartermaster General of the Army. Washington, D.C., 1898. Roll VI, Folder 65.
Norris, Frank, The Surrender of Santiago. San Francisco: Tomoye Press, 1917. This is now deposited in the Special Collections Department of Stanford University.
Parkhurst, C. D., Captain, The Artillery at Santiago. Journal 18 (Title of journal unknown), [1899?] pp. 137-192. Roll VI, Folder 65.
Report of the Commission Appointed by the President to Investigate the Conduct of the War Department in the War with Spain. Washington: Government Printing Office, 1899. Roll VI, Folder 65.
Report of the Santiago Battlefield Commission. Baltimore, Maryland: Press of John S. Bridges & Co., 1906. Roll VI, Folder 65.
Senn, Nicholas, M.D., A Thunder Storm Before Santiago de Cuba. Reprinted from the Ave Maria for April 15, 1899. Roll VI, Folder 65.
Shafter, William R., Major General, U.S.V., The Capture of Santiago, The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine. Vol. LVII, #4, February 1899, pp. 612-630. Roll VI, Folder 65.
Arrangement
While preparing the Shafter Papers for filming, a new method of organization was adopted. The Papers were placed in a chronological system arranged alphabetically within each day. Those items, such as photographs and drawings, that could not be included in a chronological framework were arranged by series. Whenever possible undated material was marked with an accurate date enclosed in brackets.
If exact dating was not possible, the documents were placed at the end of the appropriate month or year. A list of Shafter material in other repositories and a partial list of correspondents have been included in both the guide and the microfilm. An index of the Collection has been included only on the first roll of the microfilm.
Targets have been placed before documents to indicate a defective original, a duplicate, a fragment, or a folder number. Original documents have been placed before copies or translations. Enclosures follow the covering letter.
The microfilm edition of the Shafter Papers consists of seven rolls of film and represents five thousand items or 3 linear feet. It has been microfilmed in accordance with the specifications of the Technical Standards for Microfilm Documentary Publication Projects prepared by the National Historical Publications Commission. The reduction ratio in most cases is 15:1. Exceptions to the standard ratio have been indicated by targets.
Abbreviations
A.A.G. Assistant Adjutant General
Act. Acting
A.D.C. Aide-de-Camp
A.G. Adjutant General
Asst. Assistant
Brig.Gen. Brigadier General
Bvt. Brevet
Capt. Captain
Col. Colonel
C.S.A. Confederate States Army
D.A.R. Daughters of the American Revolution
Dept. Department
G.A.R. Grand Army of the Republic
Gen. General
Gov. Governor
Hdq. Headquarters
I.G. Inspector General
Lt. Lieutenant
Maj. Major
Mex. Mexico
R.R. Railroad
S.A.R. Sons of the American Revolution
Sect. Secretary
Sgt. Sergeant
Sp. Spanish
Surg. Surgeon
U.S. United States
U.S.A. United States Army
U.S.N. United States Navy
U.S.V. United States Volunteers
Vol(s). Volunteer(s)
Microfilm Edition
- ROLL I, February 10, 1862-May 5, 1898
  The William R. Shafter Collection begins with papers relating to Shafter's Civil War career, most of which are letters. The preponderance of the Civil War material dates from 1863, and includes letters written by military figures and his family. One especially notable item is a letter from Grandfather Shafter (William R.) to the young officer advising him to with prudent firmness enforce obedience to all necessary orders, as a duty they owe their country, and as much for the soldier's benefit, as for the officer's convenience. This remarkable note continues with a discussion of citizenship for Blacks: he must be restored to all the rights of citizenship as a man, of which we have so long deprived him, we must give him both freedom, and protection.
  In 1866, Shafter wrote to Edwin M. Stanton, Secretary of War, requesting an appointment to the Regular Army. Recommendations for his appointment accompany this letter and are distinguished by such signatures as Brevet Major General Clinton B. Fisk, Brevet Major General R. W. Johnson, Major J. S. Donaldson, and Major General Geore H. Thomas.
  Following the receipt of his orders of appointment to the Forty-first Infantry, U.S.A., Shafter was sent to the Texas frontier. The Shafter Papers include only a few documents extant for the years between 1876 and 1898. By April of 1876 as Lieutenant Colonel of the Twenty-fourth Infantry, he was in command of Fort Clark, Texas, and the District of the Nueces. Regular official and personal correspondence between Brigadier General E. O. C. Ord and Shafter dates from this period. Most of these papers are concerned with the pursuit of Indian and Mexican raiders into U.S. Territory. From 1876 to 1878 the problem of border raids and how to halt them occupies communications to and from such men as Brigadier General E. O. C. Ord, Major Joseph Taylor, General William T. Sherman, Major G. W. Schofield, Colonel Ranald Mackenzie, and the Mexican General Naranjo. Additionally, reports from the Seminole Negro Indian Scouts, Lieutenant John L. Bullis, and William Schuhardt describe the field conditions in the borderlands and provide military information.
  The only correspondence preserved from the 1880's is a small group of Shafter's letters to his mother. In 1890 he sent a request for a promotion to the rank of Brigadier General. Once again letters of recommendation are included with the request and bear the signatures of Major General Oliver O. Howard, John Coburn, A. P. Williams, and Major General Nelson A. Miles. Two of Miles' letters are worth noting. Both pertain to the Battle of Wounded Knee, and bring to light certain irregularities about that action. A third congratulates Shafter on his assignment to the San Francisco Presidio. There is yet another request for a promotion in 1897. In 1897 Shafter was made Brigadier General after an eighteen-year wait.
  Eighteen ninety-eight ushered in new responsibilities for Shafter. A letterpress copy of a report on the topography of the southern end of Cuba is the first document which indicates the part he was soon to play. A confidential copy of a letter signed by H. C. Corbin directs Shafter to assume command of an expedition to Cuba under the orders of Major General Miles. The remaining letters, telegrams, and orders are concerned with the camp arrangements at Tampa, Florida, and preparations for transportation of an expeditionary force to Cuba.
- ROLL II, May 6-June 6, 1898
  Letterpress copies of orders as well as printed orders, circulars, and rosters record the preparations for the expedition to Cuba. Shafter's role in the Spanish-American War expanded from commander of a reconnaisance force intended to aid the Cuban Insurgents, to commander of the Fifth Army's invasion of Santiago. A copy of a letter of May 9, 1898, imparts the information that Shafter has been promoted to Major General of Volunteers. In General Orders Number 13, Major General J. F. Wade relinquishes command of what would later be known as the Fifth Army, which Shafter commanded from May to October 1898.
  Some of the problems with which Shafter had to deal are reflected in his correspondence with Adjutant General H. C. Corbin, and R. A. Alger, Secretary of War. In one letter Corbin has inquired about Shafter's opinion on appointing noncommissioned officers of the colored regiments to the rank of captain. His reply states that the idea is acceptable to him, but admonishes, You know the unreasoning prejudice against these men and whether or not it is worth while to give cause for dissatisfaction. In another communication the conflict between military security and the people's right to know reaches a climax when censorship is brought to bear on correspondents who have published advance information on the Florida expedition.
  Secretary Alger's dispatch of May 31, 1898, contains the instructions upon which Shafter would ultimately proceed. Two documents reflect the hurry up and wait of army life: the June 4th telegram received at headquarters that reveals the sinking of the Merrimac and the presumption that Admiral Cervera was bottled up in Santiago Harbor (thereby freeing the sea lanes to the American transports); and the June 8th explanatory telegram that postponed sailing due to Spanish shipping activity in the area.
- ROLL III, June 7-July 14, 1898
  When the transports finally embarked for Cuba, the pace of correspondence quickened. Orders, telegrams, field reports, and correspondence between Shafter and such figures as Adjutant General Corbin, Secretary Alger, General Garcia, Major General Wheeler, Major General Miles, Lieutenant Colonel Roosevelt, and Clara Barton leave a record of the immense activity inherent in war-making.
  According to a note from Shafter to Admiral Sampson, the troops began to disembark on June 22, 1898. On June 25, Shafter could report that they had taken Sevilla. A telegram from President McKinley and the Secretary of War congratulates him on the action of the twenty-fifth and bears the letterhead of the Compagnie Française des Cables Télégraphies in Cuba. By July 3, El Caney and Sàn Juan had fallen to the Americans, and Santiago was closely surrounded.
  The Collection at this period is a myriad of orders pertaining to supplies, ammunition, troop placement, and casualties. It also contains documents which are simply unique. Among the latter are the receipt for one hundred and twenty prisoners taken from the Spanish cruiser, Viscaya, by Lieutenant Henicke, U.S.N., on July 3, and an entertaining letter from J. W. Moulton describing an ingenious method of removing barbed wire fence.
  The polite demands for surrender of Santiago, the first issued on July 3, and the rejections of General José Toral comprise a fascinating study of diplomatic squabbling. They also serve to remind one that honor and gentlemanly conduct were a tangible part of warfare through the nineteenth century. On July 14, 1898, Toral decided to capitulate conditionally. During the interval between July 3 and July 14, Shafter was the recipient of such items as a letter of introduction written by Miss Clara Barton, a disturbing complaint about food distribution to the troops from Theodore Roosevelt, and a report of an outbreak of yellow fever.
- ROLL IV, July 15-August 7, 1898
  The following weeks were active ones for Shafter, as is indicated by the bulk and variety of documents relating to this period. Telegrams and letters of congratulations from Major Generals Miles and Wheeler, Adjutant General Corbin, Secretary Alger, and President McKinley take their places among testimonial poems, troop rosters, lists of transports, organizational charts, and diplomatic correspondence.
  Negotiations for the surrender of Toral's forces were at a crucial point. A copy of a telegram sent by Shafter on July 15 reveals his feelings at the time: I think they fear death when they get home. We may have to fight them yet. His fears were never realized, for at ten o'clock P.M. that day Toral capitulated on the condition that his troops be returned to Spain. Shafter's subsequent telegram reads, The return to Spain of the troops in this district...closes the war in Cuba.
  In the interim between the end of the battle and the beginning of the peace, Shafter's responsibilities became even more diversified. His correspondence reflects the problems with which he was confronted. A petition from the lady refugees of El Caney dated July 14, 1898, describes the shortage of food, clothing, and water facing the civilians. A telegram from General Calixto Garcia expresses dissatisfaction on the part of Cuban military leaders that they were not included in the capitulation negotiations. Several letters from Toral, the Spanish General, indicate that he relied upon Shafter to feed his troops, supply them with medical aid, and assure their safety from the Cubans. Finally, Shafter had responsibility for the care and maintenance of his own army.